Michael P. Johnson

New York, NY

LEAD DEVOPS ENGINEER

I am an IT expert with over 16 years of professional experience. My career began as a full-time developer and slowly transitioned into a full-time SysAdmin. This range of skills has given me a unique perspective on the DevOps philosophy and how it best fits within an organization. My next career goal is to lead a team of individuals who are integrating DevOps tools into their software lifecycle.

TECHNICAL QUALIFICATIONS

Active Technical Proficiency

Amazon Web Services

EC2, ELB, AutoScaling, VPC (peering, etc), RDS, Kinesis, DynamoDB, Redshift, ElastiCache, Route53,, IAM, CloudFormation, CloudWatch, ECS, S3

Docker (Compose & Swarm), KVM, XEN, Vagrant/VirtualBox

RHEL (CentOS, Oracle Linux), Ubuntu, Arch

Chef (server and workstation), Spacewalk, Fabric, Jenkins, Zookeeper/Exhibitor, Tomcat, Flume, influxDB, Graphana, mongoDB, git, HAProxy, ActiveMQ, NSQ, Storm, GFS/GFS2, 3Par, Citrix Netscaler, Zabbix, DNS/bind, DynDNS, Cobbler, Nginx, PostgreSQL, MySQL, Storm, Sendmail/Postfix, collectd Go, Python2, Ruby (Chef), Bash/Fish

nmap, Nessus, nikto/wikto, john, ossec, OWASP ZAP, Kali Linux, Metasploit

NewRelic, PagerDuty, Sensu, PaperTrail, CircleCI

Previous Experience

VMWare, Puppet, CFengine, Varnish, Apache, LDAP, memcached, NFS, RADIUS, Shibboleth, F5 BigIP load balancer, Django, Drupal, Wordpress, Mooodle, Google Apps Admin Perl, PHP, C/C++, NodeJS, Ruby, Assembler, Java

Github Profile		
LinkedIn Profile		

EXPERIENCE

Other

Hinge App | New York, NY

Senior DevOps Engineer, December 2015 - Present

Rakuten Marketing | New York, NY 2012-2015

Senior DevOps Engineer, September 2014 - December 2015

Senior Systems Administrator, August 2012 - September 2014

Senior DevOps Engineer

Built and maintained the Enterprise Chef servers and 300+ nodes attached to them.

Responsible for team's security and penetration testing.

Built Spacewalk in-house and brought all systems under management. Security patches and testing are done in hours not days.

Implemented and evangelized DevOps principles across many areas of the organization. As a result, all servers are managed with Chef (Berkshelf, kitchen, foodcritic, etc.). Development life-cycle now begins in Kitchen/Vagrant vs. a dedicated dev environment in the data center. Deployment is done via Python/Fabric scripts. They are repeatable and tested via Jenkins.

Eliminated legacy in-house RPMs by converting all functionality to Chef cookbooks.

Created data pipeline from production systems to backend processors. The flows were built with Flume/Kafka or ActiveMQ where needed.

Key decision-maker in moving customer facing applications into AWS and closer to the end-user via DNS geolocation. Globally scaled systems to handle over 70M actions per day

Upgraded old perl CGI applications to golang as well as deprecated all Oracle databases in favor of PostgreSQL

Reengineered the real-time monitoring system in influxDB/Graphana.

Senior Systems Administrator

Maintained and extended an in-house and custom-built RPM repository to manage legacy code. Implemented newer code deployments and server provisioning with Chef. Both in-house and in AWS

Provided Tier 1 support for the organization. This covered a mixture of physical and virtualized servers running mostly RHEL clones (Oracle Linux and CentOS).

A part of the on-call rotation which monitored and supported 1000+ Xen/KVM/AWS/Physical instances across three collocated data centers and three AWS regions

Overhauled a key transaction system to respond in under 50ms, down from 2s which the legacy systems were built to handle initially.

In charge of upgrading older Xen-based servers to KVM with zero downtime for associated services. Survived Superstorm Sandy with a tethered Android phone and laptop, all customer-facing systems remained up throughout the crisis.

Key Ops person in the migration of data centers - shut down of one in NY and brought up another LV.

New York Public Radio | New York, NY

Senior Systems Administrator, July 2011 - August 2012

Responsible for all Linux administration, both on-site and in the cloud (AWS & Rackspace/Slicehost). Server management via Puppet and Fabric. Backup administration with rdiff-backup and various in-house scripts for database backups.

In charge of researching and recommending efficiency, policy and process improvements to all aspects of the IT Department. Wrote policy for desktop, server and mobile security.

Oversaw code deployment to production systems via Python/Fabric. Also supported developers working in the testing/demo environment.

On call 24x7x365 for all websites and Linux servers.

Migrated key ecommerce systems from an unstable hosting provider to a load balanced and redundant solution in Amazon's cloud (AWS).

Updated company from PCI DSS v1.2 to PCI DSS v2.0. Oversaw monthly vulnerability scans. Placed in charge of company's overall PCI compliance

Completed SANS Security 560: Network Penetration Testing and Ethical Hacking course. A detailed and rigorous course on professional and ethical penetration testing.

Performed penetration test of web services using current modern attack vectors and methodologies. Reported findings to CTO and VPs.

Pace University | New York, NY

Senior Systems Administrator, May 2010 - July 2011

Responsible for all Tier 1 Linux support on campus and oversees Tier 2 & 3 Linux support personnel. Part of on-call shift rotation responsible for 24x7 support of all servers (450+).

As the local RHCE, responsible for all Red Hat Network administration, entitlement management and all Linux boxes in the server farm.

Maintained and created Linux machines in VMWare.

Migrated two proprietary Content Management Systems (EMPower and HotBanana) running on Windows/IIS/MSSQL servers to a new Drupal based LAMP system. This required not only system planning but also significant programming (PHP and Python).

Created a high-performance computing cluster of 40 custom blades. The system supports OpenMPI as well as OpenMP. The cluster itself has 39 active nodes each running CentOS and is controlled from a central node via LAVA.

Integrated Active Directory authentication on Drupal (via the LDAP module), as well as other systems via Shibboleth.

Main admin in charge of systems in the Amazon Web Services cloud. Connected Pace's network with the cloud using a secure tunnel via an edge Linux server emulating BGP.

Built and maintained the Linux portion of the Disaster Recovery site. This includes replication of the web systems and student portal application.

Wagner College | Staten Island, NY

Director, Web and Systems Development November 2004 - May 2010

Director of Web and Systems Development; responsible for two direct reports that handle various programming projects as well as in-house training for our end users.

Responsible for HP blades, attached SAN and all system maintenance on various platforms.

Managed OS maintenance, upgrades, user management, backups, Perl/Python scripting, as well as database and system programming.

Functioned as the lead Linux Systems Administrator for the college. Often called into the Networking group for consultation on a variety of UNIX-like platforms.

Administered in-house programming (on-line applications/voting, research databases, etc.), Drupal and Moodle (Open source content/course management systems.)

Oversaw the migration of main web site from a Windows NT/IIS server to a LAMP environment. Including the training of all staff to use the new system.

Set up and maintain Single Sign On environment through LDAP, PHP and Shibboleth (SAML)

Migrated entire internal email infrastructure to Gmail. Replaced Novell Groupwise and other events calendaring with Google Calendar, and instituted a Google Docs policy.

Integrated the wireless network with Steel Belted Radius & LDAP, as well as various minor systems into the Single Sign On environment.

Developed the organization's first on-line election, and put many other internal services online

ADDITIONAL IT EXPERIENCE

Early IT career

Pangolin Web Services - Hawthorne, NJ Programmer/Systems Administrator 2000 to 2002 Bear Stearns - Whippany, NJ Intern, QA/Programmer 1999

EDUCATION AND CERTIFICATIONS

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science, Minor: Applied Mathematics

New Jersey Institute of Technology 2003

RED HAT CERTIFIED ENGINEER RHEL4-5 #804006055320640 SANS560 Network Security and Ethical Hacking Fashion Hackathon Active member of the League of Professional System Administrators OWASP NYC Chapter Member